Guide to the Ricardo Sánchez Papers, 1941-1995
Department of Special Collections
Ricardo Sánchez Papers,,
1941-1995
Special Collections M652
Sánchez, Ricardo
66 linear feet.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions:
None.
Provenance:
Purchased from Ricardo Sánchez, 1992.
BIOGRAPHY
Ricardo Sánchez was born March 29, 1941 in El Paso, Texas, the thirteenth child of a family originally from Northern New Mexico. His childhood neighborhood, El Barrio del Diablo, was an environment characterized by cultural pride (chicanismo) and familial warmth, as well as by violence, poverty, racism and alienation. Throughout his life and many travels Sánchez considered El Paso his spiritual home.
Despite a lack of encouragement at school, the young Ricardo became an avid reader and writer of poetry at an early age, with the goal of being a poet. In 1959 he dropped out of high school and enlisted in the army, where he earned a G.E.D. His service in the army ended in a dishonorable discharge and a prison sentence. After his parole in 1963 Sánchez married María Teresa Silva. In 1965, shortly before the birth of their first child, Sánchez returned to prison for armed robbery. The humiliation and frustration of his desperate struggle to support his family has been the theme of much of Sánchez's writing.
Sánchez was again paroled in 1969. This time, his "rehabilitation" was a success. Having dedicated much of his time in prison to reading and writing, Sánchez won a 1969 Frederick Douglass Fellowship for minority journalists in Richmond, Virginia, and then served as a lecturer in the School of Education at the University of Massachusetts at Amherst. In 1970 he moved to Colorado with fellow poet Abelardo Delgado to work for a Colorado migrant worker organization. By 1971 he had published a volume of poetry, Obras (Works), and in 1971 he founded Mictla Publications, a Chicano publishing house. The first book to be published by Mictla was Sánchez's Canto y grito mi liberación (I Sing and Shout My Liberation). In 1972 he began work on his Ph.D. at Union Graduate School, which he finished in 1974. For a complete account of Sánchez's widely varied professional experience, see "Resumes" (1969-1994) in Series III of the collection, Personal Papers and Memorabilia.
Throughout his academic career, Sánchez continued as a prolific poet and writer, publishing volumes of poetry as well as individual poems, fiction and articles in periodicals across the country and internationally. He also kept up a busy schedule of poetry readings and speaking engagements, and was frequently involved in conferences, exhibitions and projects of all kinds, mostly with a literary, artistic, educational or political focus. Sánchez was the author of two major syndicated columns, in the San Antonio Express-News (1985-1990) and in the El Paso Herald-Post (1988-1991), and his artistic endeavors include projects in various media, including film and television.
Sánchez was a key figure in the Chicano, Criminal Justice, and other political movements from the 1960s to the '90s. He was involved in numerous organizations, events and publications and held various positions within organizations. Information pertaining to his political involvement can be found throughout the collection, particularly in the Correspondence and Subject series. Ricardo and Teresa Sánchez had four children, Rikárd-Sergei, Libertad-Yvonne, Pedro-Cuauhtémoc (who died in infancy) and Jacinto-Temilotzín. They remained married until Ricardo Sánchez's death in September, 1995.
Major Publications:
Canto y grito mi liberación (1971)
HECHIZOspells (1976)
Milhaus Blues and Gritos Norteños (1979)
Brown Bear Honey Madness (1981)
Amsterdam Cantos y Poemas Pistos (1983)
Selected Poems (1985)
Bertrand and the Mehkqoverse (1989)
Eagle-Visioned/Feathered Adobe (1990)
SCOPE AND CONTENT
The Sánchez Papers include the personal and professional papers of Ricardo Sánchez and occupy 66 linear feet. The collection consists of 91 letter and legal length manuscript bozes, four half-sized manuscript boxes, four print boxes and eight flat boxes for over-sized materials, 18 video cassette storage boxes, three audio cassette boxes, and one map case folder. The Papers are divided into the following series:
Manuscripts by Sánchez
Correspondence
Personal Papers and Memorabilia
Subject Files
Publications by Sánchez
Manuscripts by Other Authors
Publications by Other Authors
Photographs
Audiovisual Materials
SERIES DESCRIPTION
- SERIES I: Manuscripts by Sánchez, c. 1962-1994.
  - Subseries #1. Manuscripts (Boxes 1-14)
    contains the bulk of Sánchez's manuscripts. This includes manuscripts and corrected proof copies of books and chapbooks, as well as numerous individual poems, stories and essays. Also included are manuscript copies of newspaper articles and columns, most significantly of Sánchez's two major newspaper columns, in the San Antonio Express-News (1985-1988) and the El Paso Herald-Post (1989-1991). Some files include source material, minor correspondence, and other items relating to the manuscript.
  - Subseries #2. Notebooks (Boxes 15-16)
    consists of Sánchez's personal Notebooks of poetry (largely unpublished), notes, drawings and various pasted mementos (1964-1992).
  - Subseries #3. Reporter's Notebooks (Boxes 17.1-17.2)
    consists of Reporter's Notebooks documenting Sánchez's work as a feature writer and columnist for Texas newspapers (1985-1993).
  - Subseries #4. Oversize materials (Box 124)
    consists of Oversized manuscript materials.
- SERIES II: Correspondence, c. 1962-1994.
  Incoming and outgoing correspondence between Sánchez and various friends, relatives, acquaintances, institutions and organizations, documenting Sánchez's broad interests and involvement. Correspondents include various significant writers, artists and activists.
  Many correspondence files contain outgoing letters including poetry written to correspondents by Sánchez. Also included are various manuscripts (by correspondents), publications, clippings, photos, and other items, as included in original correspondence. The Rob Lewis correspondence, for example, includes proofs and other publishing materials for Sánchez's book Amerikan Journeys::Jornadas Americanas.
  - Subseries #1. General correspondence (Boxes 18-36; box 37, folders 1-36)
    General Correspondence as described above.
  - Subseries #2. Miscellaneous and unidentified correspondence (Box 37, folders 37-47; box 38)
    Miscellaneous and unidentified correspondence. May include unidentified letters from major correspondents. Researchers are advised to browse all miscellaneous folders. Knowledgeable researchers are invited to share any identifications they may make (consult Special Collections staff).
  - Subseries #3. Legal-length correspondence (Boxes 39-43)
    Legal Length folders, listed alphabetically by correspondent.
  - Subseries #4. Photocopies of correspondence held at University of Texas at Austin (Boxes 44-46)
    Photocopies of Correspondence held by the University of Texas at Austin. Sánchez previously sold this correspondence to UTA. Photocopies are here, in the original order as listed at UTA, by date (1962-1980). This subseries includes substantial correspondence from Louis Jeantet.
- SERIES III: Personal Papers and Memorabilia, c. 1941-1994.
  This series contains various mementos and other items of personal significance to Sánchez, including financial documents, letters of recommendation, resumes, and flyers announcing his public appearances, grouped thematically and arranged alphabetically. Many items in Series III relate to events covered in detail in other series.
  - Subseries #1. General files (Boxes 47-50; Box 51, folders 1-5)
    general files (as explained above).
  - Subseries #2. Family papers (Box 51, folders 6-8; Box 52, folders 1-16)
    Family Papers. Items relating to Sánchez family history, including genealogy.
  - Subseries #3. Poster and Oversize materials (Boxes 124, 127, and map case)
    Posters and Oversized materials. Some posters may relate thematically to files in other series, but have been filed together here due to size and to their probably decorative function. Posters have been listed individually by title or subject.
- SERIES IV: Subject Files.
  This series includes information pertaining to various individuals, organizations, and issues of interest to Sánchez, in which he was involved to varying degrees. Many are Sánchez's original files. In order to preserve Sánchez's organizational schemes, and to keep items in the most appropriate intellectual order, many Subject files contain clippings, pamphlets and other publications, photos, manuscripts, and minor correspondence that would otherwise be included in other series. Also included in the Subject series are notes, pamphlets, proposals and applications written by Sánchez, for, to, or regarding different organizations and issues. Due to the large volume of such materials, and to their close relation to "subjects," they are included here rather than filed as manuscripts or publications. The Subject series, therefore, provides a broad overview of Sánchez's interests and involvement.
  A significant portion of Series IV consists of "Announcements and Programs for Cultural Events." These items, mostly flyers, are for events that Sánchez is likely to have attended or been interested in, but in which he does not seem to have been directly involved as an organizer, coordinator, or speaker. Due to limited information on such flyers, it is difficult to know what role, if any, Sánchez played in each event. There may be significant overlap between these "Announcements" and those documenting Sánchez's "Public Appearances" in Series III. Some Subject files are directly related to files in one or more other series. For example, an artist such as Nepthalí de León might have several folders of correspondence in Series II, and/or publications in Series VII, as well as some Subject folders. Subject files, in general, consist of items as originally grouped by Sánchez, to which have been added miscellaneous items that came to Stanford unattached to any correspondence.
  The Subject Series includes various "Miscellaneous" files, which contain newspaper clippings and other items pertaining to various issues, in most cases Chicano issues. These items are either broad in scope, often referring to multiple people and/or organizations, or are somewhat obscure in their focus. Researchers are advised to check these files for relevant information to compliment more specific files.
  A significant amount of space in Series IV is devoted to Paperbacks... y más, Sánchez's bookstore and cultural center in San Antonio. In addition to being a primary source of the Sánchez family's income in the 1980s, Paperbacks... y más served as a community gathering center and meeting place for poets, artists and scholars of Sánchez's acquaintance. The bookstore also sponsored and hosted "Poets of Tejas," a series of readings. The Subject files on Paperbacks... y más are Sánchez's files plus miscellaneous items. For the sake of convenience and consistency they have been kept together. They include financial papers and other documents relating to the business, correspondence, information pertaining to workshops, events, and participating poets, newspaper clippings, and various flyers, press releases and other publicity materials.
  Another large chunk of Subject files is dedicated to Union Graduate School, where Sánchez earned his Ph.D. in 1974. These files include correspondence with and papers by various Union Graduate School professors and students, as well as Sánchez's own information.
  - Subseries #1. General files
  - Subseries #2. Computer diskettes (Box 71, folders 30-35)
    computer disk (Macintosh format) and printouts, "Chiapas Packet -2/10/94." Information on Mexican history and politics c. 1992-1994 (EZLN/Zapatista Army, Chiapas Rebellion, various related organizations). The disk includes E-mail messages, radio transcripts, and other information compiled on-line into five documents. All have been printed and filed by the name of the document.
  - Subseries #3. Oversized materials (Box 125, folders 1-8)
    Oversized materials corresponding to Subject files (posters, art work, etc.).
- SERIES V: Publications by Sánchez.
  - Subseries #1. Newspaper columns and articles (Box 72, folders 1-6)
    Newspaper columns and articles. This subseries consists of photocopies of Sánchez's articles and columns (including, for convenience, letters to the editor regarding Sánchez pieces) in the San Antonio Express-News (1985-1990) and the El Paso Herald-Post (1988-1991).
  - Subseries #2. Articles and poems in periodicals (Box 72, folders 7-14; Box 73, folders 1-15)
    Articles and poems in periodicals. This subseries includes photocopies and clippings of Sánchez articles, stories and poems, as well as whole issues of periodicals including pieces by Sánchez, filed by year of publication (1969-1994). For preservation and/or organizational purposes, some periodicals containing Sánchez material have been filed by name at the end of this subseries, or in Series VII, Subseries #5 ("Publications by other authors, Rare and oversized newspapers"). In most cases, these whole issues of periodicals have been replaced in this subseries by photocopies of significant pieces.
  - Subseries #3. Books and pamphlets by Sánchez (Box 74, folders 1-9; box 126)
    Books and pamphlets by Sánchez. This subseries contains entire books (including "chapbooks," or low budget publications produced independently or by very small presses) and pamphlets by Sánchez, as well as proofs and publication materials.
  - Subseries #4. Introductions, etc. (Box 74, folders 10-16; Box 75, 1-2)
    Introductions and pieces in books Sánchez pieces in anthologies and books by other authors.
- SERIES VI: Manuscripts by other authors.
  Some files include minimal correspondence and other materials relating to and originally attached to the manuscripts.
  - Subseries #1. Mansucripts about Sánchez (Box 75, folders 3-20)
    Manuscripts about Sánchez. Includes manuscript copies of magazine and newspaper articles about Sánchez, reviews of Sánchez's books, student papers and miscellaneous essays and poems.
  - Subseries #2. Miscellaneous poetry and prose (Box 75, folders 23-33; boxes 76-80)
    Miscellaneous poetry and prose Includes articles by and about various people, organizations and issues of interest to Sánchez, many of which relate to files in other series. They are listed here by author and title.
- SERIES VII: Publications by other authors.
  - Subseries #1. Articles about Sánchez (Box 81, folders 1-14)
    Articles about Sánchez. Includes clippings and individual published articles, as well as whole issues of periodicals containing pieces on Sánchez, filed by year of publication. For preservation and organizational purposes, some periodicals featuring Sánchez have been filed in a separate subseries in Series VII: "Periodicals" (Subseries #4) or "Rare and oversized newspapers" (#5). In most cases, photocopies of articles about Sánchez are filed here in Subseries #1.
  - Subseries #2. Articles and poems (Box 81, folders 15-27; Box 82, folders 1-13)
    Articles and poems. Alphabetized by author and title.
  - Subseries #3. Books and pamphlets (Box 82, folders 14-27; Box 83; Box 84, folders 1-18)
    Books and pamphlets. Alphabetized by author and title.
  - Subseries #4. Periodicals (Box 84, folders 19-22; Boxes 85-88)
    Periodicals. Various periodicals of interest to Sánchez.
  - Subseries #5. Rare and oversized newspapers (Boxes 89-94)
    Rare and oversized newspapers. Various newspapers of interest to Sánchez, including papers produced for and relating to Chicano artistic and political movements, organizations, and issues. Many papers, especially those produced "underground" in the 1960s and '70s, are very fragile. Newspapers are filed by name.
- SERIES VIII: Photographs (c. 1940s-1990s).
  - Subseries #1. Various photographs, negatives, and slides (Boxes 95-97)
    Various photographs, negatives, and slides. Series VIII contains photographs not attached to any Correspondence or Subject files. This includes photos of numerous family members and friends, including many important Chicano artists and political figures. They document various events (readings, performances, conferences, exhibits, etc.) in Sánchez's career as a poet, teacher and activist. A substantial number of photos and slides are of art work in several media.
    Some photos came from Sánchez dated and/or identified, and some more were identified by Teresa and Rikárd Sánchez during a visit to Special Collections in the summer of 1996. Most, however, remain unidentified, and organization of this series is therefore necessarily very limited. Researchers are advised to peruse the entire series, and researchers able to make further identifications are encouraged to do so (see Special Collections staff-thanks!).
  - Subseries #2. 25th Anniversary Reenactment photographs (Box 98, folders 1-8)
    Ricardo and Teresa Sánchez 25th Anniversary Wedding Reenactment (1989). Various photos and slides.
  - Subseries #3. Scrapbooks (Box 98, folders 9-17; Boxes 99-100)
    Scrapbooks. These scrapbooks contain mementos (photos, flyers, clippings, etc.) and information on Sánchez family, friends, and events. One scrapbook contains miscellaneous photos, postcards and other items, one is Teresa Sánchez's ballet folklorico album, one is dedicated to the "Crossing Borders" conference at WSU in 1992, one to artist Jim Valdez, and one to artist Carlos Rosas. Except for the Teresa Sánchez album, which has been taken apart for preservation purposes, all scrapbooks remain in their original bindings, including accompanying loose materials. Preservation photocopies have been made of newspapers clippings and filed with the scrapbooks.
- SERIES IX: Audiovisual materials.
  Documentation of various readings, speeches, interviews, and other events and performances.
  Video and audio cassettes have been listed here as labeled by Sánchez or others, and have NOT been confirmed. Some tapes may be mislabeled or contain more or less information than is recorded. Researchers who view/listen to tapes are invited to consult with Special Collections staff, for help in using this part of the collection or in order to share any corrections or other findings. Preservation copies have been made of most video cassettes. Audio cassettes have not been copied and many are damaged or in poor condition. Researchers, please see Special Collection staff regarding preservation measures for tapes you may require.
  - Subseries #1. Video cassettes (Boxes 101-118)
    Video cassettes. Originals (boxes 101-111) are listed by number (volumes 1-104) and title. Numbers are assigned alphabetically; key word(s) chosen for alphabetization are underlined in listing. Copies follow (boxes 111-118) and are listed by volume number only.
  - Subseries #2. Audio cassettes (Boxes 119-121)
    Audio cassettes. Listed by number (volumes 1-122). Audio tapes contain documentation of readings, performances, and interviews, music by various artists, phone messages, and other audio events.
  - Subseries #3. Odd-sized audiovisual materials (Boxes 122-123)
    Odd-sized audiovisual materials. Oversized video tapes, film reels, 45" records. As with video and audio tapes, labels are uncertain.
CONTAINER LIST
- SERIES I: Manuscripts by Sánchez, c. 1962-1994.
  - Subseries #1. Sánchez manuscripts
    - "1810" (n.d.) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - "a Angelica Pérez" (1989) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - "á César, carnal" (1993) (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - "a César lo suyo" (1993) (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "a Cruz Conde" (1989) (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "a donde llegaste" (1993) (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - "a Elizabeth Estrada" (1989) (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - "a Gabino Rodríguez "(1989) (Box 1, Folder 8.1)
    - "á Gene K. Wilson" and "the notes" - originally together on note pad (1991) (Box 1, Folder 8.2)
    - "a Gloria Erika Orózco" (1989) (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - "a Jacinto Temilotzín Silva-Sánchez" (1993) (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - "a Jaime Robles" (1989) (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - "a José y Esperanza Guerrero" (1989) (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - "a Juan Raúl Flores" (1989) (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - "a Julieta Flores" (1989) (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - "a la 1920's" (1985) (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Also includes "de acuerdo a los 1920s"
    - "A los treinta - un canto a dos corazones: Norma y Felipe Durán" (1992) (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - "a María Flores" (1989) (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - "a María G. Payán (1989) (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - "a María Rosas" (1989) (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - "a Micaéla Medrano" (1989) (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - "a Ofelia J. Acosta" (1989) (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - "A Resistir" (1987) (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - "a Rosa Jácquez" (1989) (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - "a T.A.M.A.C.S." (1990) (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - ["Abelardo..." ] (1969) with "Topless" [by Abelardo Delgado?] (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - ["acribillado por los silencios..."] (1986) (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - "after 139 years" (1987) (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - "al G.E.D. y beyond" (1990) (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - "amnesty & amnesia" (1991) (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - ["Amor, ilusivo y desgraciado..."] (1969) (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - "Amsterdam Cantos y poemas pistos" (1980) - Correspondence, Introduction (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - "Amsterdam Cantos y poemas pistos" (1980) - Mailing lists for autograph party (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - "Amsterdam(n) Cantos y poemas pistos" (1980) - Typescript (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - ["and in living..."] (1981) (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - "AND SO IT'S COME TO BE" (1979) (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - ["and so we went..."] (1980) (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - ["and with a sip of aguardiente..."] (n.d.) (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - "and within the vísperas" (1979) (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - "andando por" (1979) (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - "año de carnalismo..." (1971) (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - "Años Plateados/Silvery Years" (1989) (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - "ANOTHER POEM: 5 cycles" (1962) (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - "ARTE: Una Expresión Hacia la Liberación Popular" (1978) (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Articles, El Paso Herald Post (July 1989) (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Articles, El Paso Herald Post (Aug. 1989) (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Articles, El Paso Herald Post (Sept. 1989) (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Articles, El Paso Herald Post (Oct. 1989) (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Articles, El Paso Herald Post (Nov. 1989) (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Articles, El Paso Herald Post (Dec. 1989) (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Articles, El Paso Herald Post (Jan. 1990) (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Articles, El Paso Herald Post (Feb. 1990) (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Articles, El Paso Herald Post (March 1990) (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - Articles, El Paso Herald Post (April 1990) (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - Articles, El Paso Herald Post (May 1990) (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - Articles, El Paso Herald Post (June 1990) (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - Articles, El Paso Herald Post (July 1990) (Box 1, Folder 56)
    - Articles, El Paso Herald Post (Aug. 1990) (Box 1, Folder 57)
    - Articles, El Paso Herald Post (Sept. 1990) (Box 1, Folder 58)
    - Articles, El Paso Herald Post (Nov. 1990) (Box 1, Folder 59)
    - Articles, El Paso Herald Post (Dec. 1990) (Box 1, Folder 60)
    - Articles, El Paso Herald Post (Jan. 1991) (Box 1, Folder 61)
    - Articles, El Paso Herald Post (Feb. 1991) (Box 1, Folder 62)
    - Articles, El Paso Herald Post (March 1991) (Box 1, Folder 63)
    - Articles, El Paso Herald Post (April 1991) (Box 1, Folder 64)
    - Articles, El Paso Herald Post (May 1991) (Box 1, Folder 65)
    - Articles, El Paso Herald Post (July 1991) (Box 1, Folder 66)
    - Articles, El Paso Herald Post (Jan.-June, no year) (Box 2, Folder 1)